This year was nuts, both in markets,
which I'll get into in a minute, and
personally for me. I had testicular
cancer, down to one testicle now. I had
surgery on the same day in January that
PWL Capital, the firm that I've worked
for for 12 years, announced it had been
acquired by 1 Digital. We were
previously a small privately owned
Canadian firm, now owned by a much
larger American firm. As a PWL Capital
shareholder and employee, the
acquisition was actually good news and
it's unleashed PWL's potential to
improve our offering and expand across
Canada, which has been a ton of fun.
Okay, my personal news aside, 2025 was a
wild ride. Early in the year, it looked
like we were in for a bad time, but
things turned around and returns in
stocks, gold, Bitcoin, and real estate
were not what anyone was expecting. I'm
Ben Felix, Chief Investment Officer at
PWL Capital, and I'm going to tell you
what we can learn from 2025.
I want to say a quick thank you to
everyone watching this channel. It had
by far the most views and largest
increase in subscribers since I started
posting videos here back in 2017.
I'm grateful that you all like to nerd
out with me and hope we can keep it
going in 2026.
In this video, I want to talk about some
of the unexpected things that happened
in 2025 that I think investors can learn
from. I was having a lot of
conversations in late 2024 with people
who wanted to go all in on the US stock
market, either abandoning international
diversification entirely or reducing
their exposure to Canadian and
international stocks in favor of more US
exposure. This wasn't really surprising.
At the end of 2024, the US market had
been crushing other markets for years.
For example, for the five years ending
December 31st, 2024, the US market had
outperformed the Canadian market by
nearly five percentage points
annualized. And it outperformed
international developed and emerging
markets by an even wider margin, all
measured in Canadian dollars. And that's
just five years. Go back further, 10
years, it was still a big outperformance
in the US.
In addition to that, there was plenty of
doom and gloom about Canada's stock
market and Canada's economy. We had a
productivity crisis. We had a proposed
hike to our capital gains inclusion
rate. Uh capital was fleeing the country
when Trump was elected as the 47th
President of the United States and
started threatening tariffs that could
damage Canada's economy further. All of
those concerns were exacerbated. I'm not
suggesting these are not real economic
issues. They are. But if you had read
these headlines and then not looked at
the stock market all year, you would
probably assume the Canadian market went
on to have a terrible year. That
assumption would be wrong. As of
December 17th, 2025, the Canadian stock
market index fund had returned 29.46%
since January 1st, 2025, placing it
ahead of international developed and
emerging markets and more than tripling
the Canadian dollar return on a US total
market index fund. Missing a big year
like that is hard to come back from. I
think there are a couple of important
lessons here. One is that the stock
market is not the economy. The stock
market prices forward-looking
information about the expected future
cash flows of businesses. The economy
does affect those expected future cash
flows, but economic data are
backward-looking. By the time we hear a
headline about Canada's economy, the
market has likely already priced it in
months prior. If economic data end up
being bad, but better than what the
market had been expecting, we can even
see a rise in stock prices on bad
economic news. It's crazy to think
about. This makes basing investment
decisions on economic news a pretty bad
idea most of the time. The other related
lesson is that while the future is hard
enough to predict, future stock returns
are probably even harder. Some news,
like unexpected tariffs, can affect
stock prices in the short term. Looking
back to early 2025, it seemed like
tariffs would be putting significant
downward pressure on all stock markets.
Again, the market is always looking
ahead. A shock like tariffs can result
in stock prices falling on the news, but
as new information about the actual
impact of tariffs become known, markets
adjust. The US stock market was down
more than 16% in Canadian dollar terms
in April 2025.
One of the things I said in a video
earlier this year, around that time,
looking at historical data for the US
stock market, was that negative
intra-year returns don't always predict
negative returns for the year.
It's not uncommon for stocks to enter
negative territory at some point during
the year, while then finishing the year
with positive returns. And that is
exactly what we saw in 2025. This is one
of the many reasons that sticking to
your long-term plan is generally much
better than trying to get in and out of
the market or otherwise changing your
portfolio based on whatever might be
happening in the world around you. I
think the other big lesson here is that
international diversification is still
not dead. There's been an increasing
perception that the US stock market is
the only market that anyone needs to
invest in. I and many other people
smarter than me have been saying for
years now that international
diversification continues to be one of
the most important principles for
long-term investors, despite the recent
outperformance of the US market. 2025
was a good reminder of why this is true.
A single country stock market, including
the US market, can go through both short
and long periods of poor performance.
The US lost decade wasn't all that long
ago, but it's easily forgotten. In those
periods, international diversification
often pays off, as it did this year.
Canada's incredible stock returns this
year seem to have largely gone
unnoticed. The other story that I've not
seen mentioned much is the returns of
Canadian value and small-cap value
stocks, which have had an even bigger
year than the Canadian market as a
whole. The iShares S&P TSX Small Cap
Index ETF returned 47.94%
from January 1st through December 17th,
2025, and the iShares Canadian Value
Index ETF returned 33.63%.
I know it doesn't make sense to focus on
one year of returns, but the crazy thing
here is that if we looked at the data a
year ago, the 10-year returns of
Canadian value and small-cap stocks
trailed the market. Value stocks were
only a little bit behind. Small caps
were way behind. Fast forwarding to
December 17th, 2025, so now we're
looking at just under 11 years of data
from the same starting point, Canadian
value has now outperformed for the full
period, and while small caps are still
trailing the market, it's a lot closer
than it was. The lesson here is that if
you believe in an investment strategy,
staying in your seat is extremely
important. Returns often come in short
spurts. Missing out on them is easy to
do if you don't stay invested, and
missing out is very hard to recover
from. It's kind of like getting up to
pee during a hockey game and missing a
big goal. The small cap and value
examples are of particular interest to
me. While I am a big believer in total
market index funds, and I talk about
them on the on this channel all the
time, that is not how I invest my money
or the money of most of PWL Capital's
clients. We use funds from a company
called Dimensional Fund Advisors, which
look a lot like total market index
funds, but they tilt toward small-cap,
value, and highly profitable companies.
That approach has struggled at times in
recent history, but the Dimensional
Canadian Equity Funds similarly had a
big year in 2025 due to their exposures.
People get annoyed when I bring up
Dimensional Funds because they're not
available directly to DIY retail
investors in Canada, but on that point,
I have some really good news. Avantis
Investors, a direct competitor to
Dimensional Fund Advisors, is partnering
with CIBC to launch a suite of
Canadian-listed ETFs. Like Dimensional,
Avantis Funds are very similar to index
funds in principle. They're low cost,
broadly diversified, and tax efficient,
but they have a more flexible
implementation approach, and unlike a
total market index fund, which holds
stocks at their market capitalization
weights, Avantis uses financial economic
theory and evidence to tilt toward
small-cap, value, and highly profitable
stocks. These tilts are designed to
increase expected long-term returns. The
big development here is that while
Dimensional Funds in Canada are only
available through advisors like PWL
Capital, Avantis ETFs will be available
directly to retail investors. I used
US-listed Avantis ETFs in my old model
portfolios that were designed to give
retail investors in Canada a way to
implement this investment approach. I
will definitely make a dedicated video
when I have something more to talk
about. We do know the fees listed in the
preliminary prospectus, which look very
reasonable. The Avantis CIBC All Equity
Asset Allocation ETF has an annual
management fee of 0.28%.
This is not the MER, to be clear, the
management expense ratio, which includes
other costs and taxes in it. For
example, XEQT has a management fee of
0.18% and an MER, management expense
ratio, of 0.2%.
Even if the Avantis fund comes in at
0.35%
uh for the MER, it still looks pretty
good for what you're getting. It's like
uh like an asset allocation fund that
looks a lot like VEQT or XEQT, but it's
got built-in tilts toward small-cap,
value, and high-profitability stocks.
Based on the preliminary prospectus, it
will have a long-term strategic asset
mix of 45% US stocks, 32% Canadian, 15%
international developed, and 8% emerging
markets. Again, very similar to an XEQT
or a VEQT. This is definitely a
development to watch in 2026 if you're
as much of a nerd as I am. To be clear,
I'm not affiliated with or being paid by
Avantis, and I gain nothing from you
using their products in Canada or in the
US. I just think this is good news for
the nerdiest of us Canadian investors
who want an easy-to-use evidence-based
alternative to low-cost total market
index funds. Gold has had an incredible
year. The iShares Gold Bullion ETF
returned 57.53%
in Canadian dollar terms from January
1st through December 17th, 2025. I have
never been a proponent of holding gold
in portfolios for the simple reason that
it's not a productive asset with a
meaningfully positive expected return.
Gold has long-term returns. By
long-term, I mean 100 years or longer,
roughly in line with inflation, maybe a
little higher. Short-term returns will
fluctuate wildly around its real value
and a mixed track record as a hedge
against bad markets and inflation. Its
place in a portfolio is not obvious to
me unless you have a belief that its
price will go up while you hold it,
which to be fair worked out great for
people who were holding it this year. As
Warren Buffett has said, what motivates
most gold purchases is their belief that
the ranks of the fearful will grow. It
makes sense to buy gold if you think
other people are going to want to buy
gold in the future. I don't love that
reason to invest in something, which is
why I don't hold it or suggest holding
it. The question I keep getting based on
gold's returns this year is whether my
views on gold have changed in light of
its recent performance. I am totally
open to updating my beliefs when I
receive new information, but I would not
consider high short-term returns to be
sufficient new information to update a
prior belief that gold has low expected
returns. Academic research using huge
amounts of data and applying economic
theory suggests that gold has an
expected return of around 1% above
inflation. And that's on the high end of
the estimates I've seen, which is
roughly what its historical return has
been, at least over the sample period in
that paper. When we look back through
history, gold has had big jumps in price
before, and the most common outcome of
the resulting high gold prices is lower
future gold returns, bringing its real
value and its long-term returns back in
line with its long-term historical
performance. I'm not predicting a gold
crash, but I think the data on this do
warrant caution for anyone who's enticed
by its recent returns.
If you have been holding gold,
congratulations on a great year. If
you're looking at gold's recent high
returns and just now considering buying
gold, I think it's worth remembering
that investors have a tendency to buy
things after they have done well and
sell after they have done poorly,
leading to bad investment outcomes.
I don't mean that nobody should invest
in gold right now, but I do mean that
you should have a very good
understanding of why you want to invest
in gold right now, other than the fact
that it's gone up a whole bunch
recently, and keep in mind that the base
rate expected long-term return return
for gold is low.
Bitcoin went in the opposite direction
this year. The Purpose Bitcoin ETF
dropped 13.09%
in Canadian dollar terms from January
through December 17th, 2025. For similar
reasons to gold, I've never been a
proponent of including Bitcoin in
long-term portfolios.
This one bad year doesn't prove
anything. It doesn't mean I was right.
Obviously, Bitcoin's gone up a ton other
than this year so far. Uh but Bitcoin's
divergence from gold over a period with
lots of geopolitical uncertainty, where
Bitcoin's kind of meant to shine, was
pretty interesting to see. We'll We'll
see what happens in the future. Another
story from 2025 that I don't think is
getting enough attention is the
continued drop in real estate prices and
rents in some of Canada's largest
cities. It was not that long ago that
real estate going up seemed like a
constant fact of life in Canada and
rents going up. But things like changes
to our immigration policies and a rise
in interest rates have put a ton of
pressure on the demand for housing in
some cities. From the 2022 peak,
composite real estate prices in Toronto,
that's combining all types of housing in
Toronto, had fallen nearly 26% through
November 2025. From January through
November 2025, so just this year up
until November, that drop was 6.5
percentage points. A common narrative
that I've heard here is that most of
this drop is coming from the tiny
shoebox apartments that were overbuilt
in Toronto, but the peak to trough drop
in single-family homes has actually been
a larger in percentage terms than the
drop for apartments. Prices in other
cities have been more resilient, but
2025 was a tough year across the board.
An interesting related topic is the
status of hypothetical renter and owner
wealth across Canada. Earlier this year,
I did a video and a paper comparing a
hypothetical renter and owner in 12
Canadian cities using real data on
rents, house prices, inflation, and
stock returns from 2005 through 2024.
So, I had this hypothetical uh renter
who was deciding, do I keep renting or
do I buy a house? And if they kept
renting, they invested in the stock
market. If they bought, they they bought
the house.
And then they saved and invested. The
renter saved and invested the cost
difference between renting and owning
over time. Then I just tracked how did
their wealth evolve over this full
period?
The analysis at that time showed mixed
results, with renting leading to more
wealth in some cities, but not in
others. And on average across all cities
that I looked at, it was basically a
tie. There was a tiny tiny advantage for
owning. I measured the outcome as the
ratio of renter wealth to owner wealth,
so a number above one means the renters
were better off, and below one means the
owners were better off.
The average owner uh the average renter
to owner wealth ratio, as you can see,
is uh was 0.99 at the end of 2024.
And then so far in 2025, real estate is
down, as I mentioned. Rents are flat or
maybe down a bit, and stock markets are
way up. I will do a full update once I
have the year-end data for 2025, but as
of November, renting is beating owning
on average across the 12 cities, with an
average renter to owner wealth ratio of
1.14.
Again, above one means renters have more
wealth than owners on average across
these 12 cities.
In some cities that previously had a
huge advantage for owners over renters
in the sample, uh like over the original
2005 to 2024 sample,
uh Victoria and Kitchener being the big
Kitchener-Waterloo being the biggest
examples, that gap, the the uh wealth
gap between owners and renters,
has narrowed to close to zero.
I want to be clear that this does not
mean that owning a place to live is bad.
I own my house. I've probably taken a
beating financially recently, too. I'm
okay with that because I like my house.
My point on renting and versus owning
has always been that renting is not a
bad financial decision as long as the
renter saves diligently and and invests
in a portfolio with sufficiently high
expected returns,
like a total stock market index fund
portfolio. 2025 has put an exclamation
point on that point. Right now, as the
year comes to a close, investors seem to
be mostly worried about the high
valuations and market concentration in
the US stock market. The top seven
stocks in the US market make up 32% of
the market's total value, which is the
highest level of market concentration
going back to 1927.
I don't think that market concentration
is something to worry about. Many other
countries around the world have had and
currently do have more concentrated
stock markets than the US market without
it resulting in poor returns for those
countries. Even within the US market,
the historical relationship between
current market concentration and future
returns is weak at best and
statistically insignificant. High stock
valuations could be more of an issue.
Historically, looking at 10 developed
countries, there is a clear relationship
between high current valuations and low
future returns. The relationship is not
statistically reliable, but it's clearly
there. You can see in the chart. The
thing is, even if valuations do have
some information about future returns,
they do not predict the future. It's
possible for high current valuations to
be followed by high future returns, as
the US market has proven in recent
history and other countries have
demonstrated in the past. I don't think
high stock valuations are a market
timing signal. They They don't say you
should get out of this stock market
right now, but they should lead to more
moderate expected returns for that stock
market. When you're thinking about what
returns do I expect from this part of my
portfolio, a country with high stock
valuations, you might want to use lower
expected returns, but that doesn't mean
that the future returns are actually
going to be low, so I wouldn't suggest
trying to time the market based on that
information.
The last comment I have as we close out
2025 is that investors are being
increasingly inundated with what I'm
calling ETF slop.
Issuers ETF ETF issuers are launching a
ton of complex and risky ETFs and
marketing them really aggressively to
retail investors through influencer
campaigns and social media ads.
I'm pretty confident saying that most
investors don't need Buffett ETFs, which
I will do a video on next year,
single-stock covered call ETFs,
leveraged single-stock ETFs, or
leveraged covered call ETFs. Like, what
are we even doing? The ETF industry
needs to make money, which is fine.
Low-cost index funds are not a
profitable business for most ETF
issuers. Index funds are literally
available for free, at least in one
case, from Fidelity. The result is that
issuers who want to make money need to
come up with products that they can
charge higher fees on and that investors
will want to buy. We end up with a whole
bunch of ETF products designed to cater
to the emotional and cognitive biases of
investors, not to give them the best
chance at meeting their long-term
financial goals. I'm Ben Felix, Chief
Investment Officer at PWL Capital. Enjoy
the holidays and I'll see you in 2026.